

Expertise:

Agile Methodologies Project Management Product Management Full Lifecycle Project Planning Story Mapping Extreme Programming Getting Things Done (GTD) **Business Process Modeling** Enterprise Architecture Testing Methodologies Systems Implementation Systems Integration Training Analysis and Design Open Source Software Ruby on Rails Web 2.0 Paper Prototyping

Industries:

Web Based Applications Consumer Software Financial Services Construction Shipping Insurance

Computer Languages:

Ruby, JavaScript, CSS, Java, .NET(C#), Python, C++/C, PHP, Perl, Pascal, Lisp

Education:

University of Southern California BS in Computer Science

<u>jeremy.lightsmith@gmail.com</u> <u>http://onemanswalk.com/</u>

10100 4th Ave NW Seattle, WA 98177 USA

JEREMY LIGHTSMITH (formerly Jeremy Stell-Smith)

Executive Summary

Software professional with over 11 years imagining, organizing, and building software products and teams that benefit from uncommon attention to the human dynamic involved.

I have spent most of my career working on and toward agile & lean teams in quickly changing environments where communication is critical. I have a solid track record of driving projects to successful release and a diversity of experience across a range of industries.

I have a history of results that is very strong technically but also filled with examples of bringing people together in highly performant and interdependent teams. I excel at building relationships, driving to requirements, engendering trust and both facilitating and leading these teams.

Experience

Pivotal Labs, 2007 - present

Pivotal provides on-demand project teams for well funded web 2.0 startups. My responsibilities at Pivotal include Client / Project Management, Agile Enablement / Coaching of development teams, and Ruby on Rails development. I also introduced the practice of Agile Inceptions to the company, which they have instituted before the start of every project.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / COACH / LEAD, Client: Knowledge Management Company

I managed client relationship and led one of Pivotal's largest development teams (12 devs) to create a site capable of serving terabytes of information to web browsers, iphones, and other mobile devices in 4 months. I started it by leading an inception, and saw it through to launch.

ARCHITECT / SENIOR DEVELOPER, Client: Custom Book Publishing Company

I helped bring site from concept to launch in 3 months. I implemented much of its web 2.0 frontend and rails backend, including a scaleable AWS architecture, capable of supporting thousands of concurrent users, ordering, customizing, and printing books.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / COACH / LEAD, Client: Major Construction Company

I was responsible for a systems implementation of a punchlist product from inception to launch. I led requirements gathering sessions, led development, and collaborated closely with its customers to see it through to a successful 1.0 release. Replacing a previous system, the new system is up to 10 times more responsive, scales to millions of records, handles concurrent users and offline access, and was delivered on time and on budget.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / COACH / LEAD, Client: Construction Services Company

I managed the client relationship and led development of their flagship product. My team of 2-6 completed a ruby on rails rewrite and data migration of this multiyear legacy Java system in 6 months. I collaborated with my client's clients to sell, design and develop new products.

SENIOR DEVELOPER, Product: Pivotal Tracker

As a senior developer, I was responsible for much of a UI overhaul as we pushed it toward full public release.

ThoughtWorks Inc., 2000-2007

As an Extreme Programming Coach, I concentrated on gelling teams and introducing Agile Best Practices as well as mentoring developers and business analysts. As a developer, I was responsible for evolving much of the architecture on each of my projects at ThoughtWorks. During my time here, I taught unit testing workshops, hosted the Bay XP User Group, presented at various conferences, co-started the first GeekNight, and even got a chance to pair with people like Ward Cunningham, Martin Fowler, Robert Martin, and Brian Marick.

LEAD FACILITATOR / TRAINER, QuickStart Engagements

Led several QuickStarts and developed and taught internal classes to train other facilitators. In this type of engagement, a small ThoughtWorks team facilitates intense working meetings with stakeholders, BAs and developers to drive out clear business goals and objectives, and eventually flesh out enough requirements to kickoff an agile project. The projects that I started this way ranged from small 4 person projects to 30 person, multimillion dollar projects lasting multiple years.

DEV LEAD / PRODUCT OWNER, Product: CruiseControl.rb

Led a small development team to design and implement a ruby version of cruise control. We drove the product to a successful 1.0 release and beyond under schedule. It is now the de facto standard for ruby continuous integration, in use in hundreds of projects around the world. I remain active as a lead developer today of this open source project.

PRODUCT CONSULTANT, Client: Language Workbench Product Company

Drove requirements and did research for a next generation IDE for developing Domain Specific Languages. Served as a source of industry knowledge and best practices for this developer tool.

AGILE COACH / SENIOR ARCHITECT, Client: Major Financial Company

As the project coach, I was responsible for evolving the process that grew the team from 5 architects on a pilot project to the eventual roll out of 30 developers spread across 3 sites. As an architect, I was responsible for much of the architecture which Microsoft published in the early days of .NET development.

SENIOR DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD, Client: Major Petroleum Company

I helped define methodology and architecture on this 100+ person project developing a bespoke oil trading application. I also contributed significantly to a custom pre-hibernate persistence layer and wrote the data migration framework used for migrating over 100 legacy tables on release.

AGILE COACH / DEV LEAD, Client: Container Shipping Web Service

I introduced XP and other best practices to the project & client. I also pioneered n-stage XSL transforms, developed a powerful framework for writing web applications, and rewrote and optimized an entity bean code generator.

IBM Corp., 1999-2000

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD

I led the Windows GUI team on a large-scale cross-platform C++/Java environment. I led development of Testing Frameworks, User Wizards, and Dynamic Control Resizing for Internationalization.

Intel Corp., 1998

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (INTERN)

I developed a feature-rich IDE for non-programmer chip testers to write test scripts. I also collaborated with an external vendor to develop a commercial Failure Analysis Tool.

Microsoft Corp., 1997

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER IN TEST (INTERN), Expedia

As part of the Expedia team, I was responsible for the development of a database stress-testing tool with an MFC interface, and limited "Smart Monkey"/ Al functionality.

University of Southern California, 1995-1999

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, Robotics Lab

In my time with the Robotics Lab, I worked on an behavioral AI software for directing small robots and a real-time 3D physical simulation of a human torso.

Other Relevant Professional & Community Experience

FacilitationPatterns.org 2008-present

AUTHOR

As a facilitator I have learned and use many tips, tricks, and approaches that enable me to be effective. Patterns provide a vehicle to transmit that information to someone else. I hope to one day turn this site with my growing collection of facilitation patterns into a book.

Burn Blue 2007-present

CO-FOUNDER / DIRECTOR

Burn Blue is a non-profit, community-run organization for the promotion of blues dancing in Seattle. As a co-founder, and now director, my contributions to burn blue are its focus on community involvement & growth, its pragmatism and risk management strategies. We started the Seattle's first weekly blues dance, grew the scene by an order of magnitude, and demonstrated that blues dance can be profitable for teachers, DJs and organizers.

Marathon 2002-2003

CO-FOUNDER / PRODUCT MANAGER

I started this project at a client to address the brittleness of their product. It then grew to an open source project that I led and ran as an XP project with a team of up to 6 developers for over a year. It is still one of the most widely used open source testing tools for java swing.

Various Local and National Blues Dance Events 2005-present

ORGANIZER / TEACHER

I organize dance events at a national level, often coordinating registration, housing, classes, bands, etc for hundreds of dancers. I also teach dance locally and travel to teach it nationally at events around the country.

References available upon request